<?xml version="1.0"?>

<document>

  <properties>
    <title>OpenEdge Modules</title>
    <author email="eelco.hillenius@openedge.nl">Eelco Hillenius</author>
  </properties>

  <body>

    <section name="About this Guide">
      <p>
        The OpenEdge User Guide is intended to help developers get acquainted with the
		OpenEdge Modules framework. If you have any
        suggestions or comments please feel free to post them to the
        <a href="mailto:todo@sourceforge.net">list</a>.
      </p>
    </section>
  <section name="Overview">
    <p>
    The <code>OpenEdge module framework</code> provides for an easy to use lightweight container for 
	components and Jobs.
	</p>
	<p>
	Key features are:
	<ul>
		<li>
			Lightweight. You can use it in the environment you want (J2EE/ standard) and the internals
			of the framework are not too difficult to understand as it's aims are not sky-high (it is not intended to be the
			mother of all frameworks).
		</li>
		<li>
			Easy to use. You will be up and running in less than an hour.
		</li>
		<li>
			Flexible. It is relatively easy to plugin your own types and commands and behaviour 
			that goes with them
		</li>
		<li>
			Non (too) intrusive. Allthough for specific behaviour you have to implement specific interfaces, you do not
			have to implement any interface at all for your components. 
			The lately very populair pattern IoC (Inversion of Control) applies to parts of this framework.
		</li>
		<li>
			Wraps the excellent J2EE-ready sceduling framework 'Quartz' 
			(<a target="_new" href="http://www.part.net/quartz.html">see their website</a>). With Quartz
			you have the power of a mature, production ready sceduler. OpenEdge Modules
			facilitates in easy configuration of Jobs and Triggers, and starts the sceduler for you, but does this
			in the least intrusive manner possible. You can write jobs as usual for Quartz and the only
			thing you have to do is configuring them (which you otherwise have to do programmatically).
		</li>
	</ul>
	</p>
	

  </section>

</body>
</document>

