<?xml version="1.0"?>
<document>

	<properties>
		<title>OpenEdge Baritus</title>
		<author email="eelco.hillenius@openedge.nl">Eelco Hillenius</author>
	</properties>

	<body>

		<section name="Alternatives">
			<p>
				If you are looking for a Java web application framework, but Baritus is just not
				your cup of tea, take a look at the following projects.
				<ul>
					<li>
						<a href="http://java.sun.com/j2ee/javaserverfaces/index.jsp">Java Server Faces (JSF)</a>.
						This recent standard is aimed towards facilitating the development op Java
						web application in a component oriented fashion.
						<a href="http://www.myfaces.org/">MyFaces</a> is the current OSS initiative. 
						It is quite active and works better with a lot of different servers than the 
						<a href="http://java.sun.com/j2ee/javaserverfaces/download.html">JSF reference implementation</a>.
						IMHO it's too bad that currently JSF seems to be very JSP centric. Though implementations
						do not have to be JSP based, that is probably where tool developpers will be heading.
					</li>
					<li>
						<a href="http://mav.sourceforge.net/">Maverick</a>
						If you think Baritus does not add much to the original minimalist framework, you could
						give Maverick a try. It works great and is easy to extend.
					</li>
					<li>
						<a href="http://jakarta.apache.org/struts/">Struts</a>.
						The leading and first to popularize web MVC framework. Struts has a huge user base, lots of
						documentation and extensions and your manager has probably heard of it.
					</li>
					<li>
						<a href="http://www.opensymphony.com/webwork/">WebWork</a>.
						Number two in popularity, webWork 2 uses the generic command pattern framework XWork
						and is based on a concept they call Pull HMVC.
					</li>
					<li>
						<a href="http://jakarta.apache.org/tapestry/index.html">Tapestry</a>.
						A very elegant framework that has a component focus instead of a page focus. 
						It has support in Eclipse using the 
						<a href="http://spindle.sourceforge.net/">Spindle plugin</a>.
					</li>
					<li>
						<a href="http://www.springframework.org/">Spring Framework</a>.
						A relatively new kid on the block, Spring Framework has a strong business focus, and is
						very flexible in the kind of techniques you want to combine it with.
					</li>
					<li>
						<a href="http://barracudamvc.org/Barracuda/index.html">Barracuda</a>.
						Though it looks quite complicated to me, it also looks like a very sophisticated
						framework. Take a look at their very informative framework analysis
						<a href="http://barracudamvc.org/Barracuda/docs/barracuda_vs_struts.html">here</a>.
					</li>
				</ul>
			</p>
			<p>
				Drop us a line if you think another framework should be listed here as well.
			</p>
		</section>

	</body>
</document>
