<?xml version="1.0"?>
<document>

  <properties>
    <title>Using OpenEdge Access</title>
    <author email="eelco.hillenius@openedge.nl">Eelco Hillenius</author>
  </properties>

  <body>
	
    <section name="Using OpenEdge Access">
      <p>
		OpenEdge Access is really just a thin wrapper for the
		JAAS (Java Authentication and Authorization Service)
		framework. Basically, what OpenEdge Access does is:
		<ul>
			<li>
				Provide a means to add your own security policy to the
				current collection of policies
			</li>
			<li>
				Provide a means to add LoginModules to the current collection 
				of LoginModules
			</li>
		</ul>
      </p>
	  
      <subsection name="Specifics">
		<p>
			Authentication with JAAS is done by providing an implementation of the 
			JAAS LoginModule. This framework not only gives you a default, ready to use 
			implementations of LoginModule, but also provides a mechanism to add LoginModule 
			implementations and policies to the JVM dynamically.
		</p>
		<p>
			For authorisation in web application environments, the <code>javax.servlet.Filter</code> 
			implementation and <code>javax.security.auth.login.LoginContext</code> wrapper are 
			given to provide a default way of doing authorization. 
		</p>
		<p>
			The non-JAAS interface <code>UserManager</code> and it's (possible) implementations 
			provide for default user/ role managent. This gives users an out of the box 
			implementation of basic user- and role managent that, possibly combined with a 
			application specific implementation of <code>LoginDecorator</code>, is 
			probably sufficient for most cases of authorisation in applications. 
		</p>
	  </subsection>

      <subsection name="Word of warning">
		<p>
			You have to know that if you use the framework to add policies or login modules,
			it will be VM-wide. This is a special point of attention if you develop webapplications,
			as webapplications within a server share the same VM.
		</p>
		<p>
			Be sure that:
			<ul>
				<li>
					Names of the login modules are unique within the VM
				</li>
				<li>
					Policies you add do not impose security threats or conflics
					with other policies.
				</li>
			</ul>
		</p>
		<p>
			You can use the JAAS framework without using this framework, but you then
			would have to configure the login modules and policies in a server dependend
			manner (whereas the JAAS framework is standard Java).<br/>
			You can still use JAAS, the UserManager and the securityfilter without
			adding the login modules and policies at runtime; just configure those things
			with your server.
		</p>
	  </subsection>

	  
   </section>
 </body>
</document>
