<?xml version="1.0"?>
<document>

  <properties>
    <title>Extending OpenEdge Modules</title>
    <author email="eelco.hillenius@openedge.nl">Eelco Hillenius</author>
  </properties>

  <body>
    <section name="Building Maven">
      <p>
        Building Maven is a little different than your typical Java
        build because Maven uses itself to build itself!  Thus, in order
        to successfully build Maven, a bootstrapping process is required
        to jumpstart the build.  Fortunately, the details of this have
        been encapsulated in a separate build file called
        <code>build-bootstrap.xml</code>.  This document details the
        necessary steps to successfully build Maven from source.  After
        completing the process, not only will Maven be built, it will
        also be installed on your system, which will enable you to build
        any other Maven-enabled project (i.e. all Turbine projects).
      </p>
      <p>
        Before you can build Maven, you'll need to make sure you have <a
        href="http://jakarta.apache.org/ant/">Ant</a> 1.5 or higher
        installed on your system.  Don't forget to install the
        <code>optional.jar</code> included with Ant.  In addition,
        you'll also need the <a href="http://www.junit.org/">JUnit</a>
        unit testing framework installed.  Be sure to install
        <code>junit.jar</code> in your <code>$ANT_HOME/lib</code>
        directory.  Failure to do so will result in build errors.
      </p>
      <p>
        You also must have the <code>$MAVEN_HOME</code> env-var set. The
        Maven installation is encapsulated in the <code>$MAVEN_HOME</code>
        directory: scripts, Maven's run-time library, plug-ins and the
        local repository.
      </p>
      <p>
        For the impatient reader that doesn't want to read the rest of
        this document, type the following:
      </p>
      <source><![CDATA[ant -f build-bootstrap.xml]]></source>
      <p>
        If you are new to Maven, it is recommended that you read the
        rest of the document as it explains the build process in a
        little more detail.
      </p>
      <p>
        If you are behind a proxy, you must define proxy parameters for
        building Maven :
        <a href="../faq.html#build-firewall">FAQS</a>.
      </p>
      <subsection name="Bootstrapping Maven">
        <p>
          Before you can begin the process, you'll need to download the
          source from the <code>maven</code> CVS
          repository.  If you are not familiar with the Jakarta CVS
          repositories, please see the <a
          href="http://jakarta.apache.org/site/cvsindex.html">documentation</a>.
        </p>
        <p>
          After setting the value of <code>$MAVEN_HOME</code> and
          pulling down the sources you are now ready to
          build and install Maven on your system using the bootstrapping
          process.  As mentioned earlier, the bootstrapping process is
          defined in <code>build-bootstrap.xml</code>, and can be
          initiated by typing the following:
        </p>
        <source><![CDATA[ant -f build-bootstrap.xml]]></source>
        <p>
          Thats it! Congratulations!  You have now built Maven with
          Maven and installed Maven on your system!  What does that
          mean?  
        </p>
        <ul>
          <li>
            The Maven build system has been installed in
            <code>$MAVEN_HOME</code>.
          </li>
          <li>
            The Maven JAR has been installed in your local repository,
            which defaults to <code>$MAVEN_HOME/repository</code>, so
            that plug-ins that might require Maven can build and it
            is installed in Maven's run-time directory.
          </li>
          <li>
            You can now build any Maven-enabled project with ease!
            Please see the <a href="use.html">Using Maven</a>
            document for instructions on how to build Maven-enabled
            projects.
          </li>
          <li>
            You can now integrate Maven into your own projects!  Please
            see the <a href="integrate.html">Integrate Maven</a>
            document for instructions on how to do this.
          </li>
        </ul>
      </subsection>
    </section>
  </body>
</document>
